Guide to the Peter Pelham papers, 1962-1982 MVC0011.MS
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Peter Pelham collection
1962-1982
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MVC0011.MS
5.5 Linear Feet
Peter Pelham was the fifth president of Mount Vernon Seminary and Junior College, originally founded in Washington, D.C. in 1875. Mount Vernon Seminary and College merged with The George Washington University in 1999. This collection contains correspondence, and administrative files from the collection of Peter Pelham, president of Mount Vernon Seminary from 1962-1976.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: Correspondence, Development and strategic planning files, Special event files, Administrative files 1975-1977, and Administrative files.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Mount Vernon Seminary and College archives were acquired by GWU upon merger with Mount Vernon College. The collection was transferred to the Foggy Bottom campus in 2009.
Biographical / Historical
Peter Pelham served as the fifth President of Mount Vernon Seminary and Junior College from 1962-1976.
Pelham graduated from Williams College, received his MA from Harvard University, served in the United States Air Force, and worked for three years as assistant director of admissions at Williams.
During Pelham's presidency, Mount Vernon Seminary was disestablished and the institution's name was officially set as Mount Vernon Junior College. In 1970, the Florence Hollis Hand Chapel was dedicated. Mount Vernon College receives initial accreditation as a four-year college during Pelham's turn.
Peter Pelham resigned in September 1976.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains files produced during the time Peter Pelham served as President of Mount Vernon Seminary and Junior College, including personal correspondence, logistical information about special events, and files produced by various strategic planning committees. The materials range in date from 1962 to 1982.
Women's colleges; Women -- Education; Pelham, Peter; Mount Vernon Seminary; Mount Vernon College
- Correspondence, 1962-1977; Series 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains correspondence to and from Peter Pelham. The materials in this series date from 1962-1977.
  - Commission on curriculum correspondence, 1970-1971; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Current parents, 1976-1977; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Faculty and staff memos and correspondence, 1974; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Foxhall Road--Peter Pelham interview and correspondence, invitation, 1962-1976; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters of recommendation #1, 1975-1976; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters of recommendation #2, 1975-1976; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1962-1975; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mr. Pelham correspondence-November, 1976; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Mr. Pelham correspondece-December, 1976; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Mr. Pelham correspondece-January, 1977; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Mr. Pelham correspondece-February, 1977; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Mr. Pelham correspondece-March, 1977; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Mr. Pelham correspondece-April, 1977; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Mr. Pelham correspondece-May, 1977; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Mr. Pelham correspondece-June, 1977; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Personal correspondence A-D #1, 1976-1977; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Personal correspondence A-D #2, 1976-1977; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Personal correspondence E-I, 1976-1977; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Personal correspondence J-R #1, 1976-1977; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Personal correspondence J-R #2, 1976-1977; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Personal correspondence J-R #3, 1976-1977; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Personal correspondence S-Z, 1976-1977; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Secondary schools correspondence, 1976-1977; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Development and strategic planning files, 1964-1977; Series 2
  The materials in this series contain files concerning the long range plann for and development of Mount Vernon Seminary and Junior College, including files on building, Middle States, curriculum, etc. The materials date from 1964-1977.
  - Buildings and grounds--general, 1964-1976; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Continuing education, 1972-1973; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Commission on curriculum, 1970-1971; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Final report--the ad hoc committee for the evaluation of new programs, 1970; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Friends of Mount Vernon Seminary, 1965-1966; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Friends of Mount Vernon Seminary, 1966-1975; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Long range development plan, 1966; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Long range planning, 1964; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Long range planning conversations with Dean Meder, April 19, 1964; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Master site plan, 1966; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Men's committee, 1977; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Middle States Association--evaluation report February 18-19, 1968; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous files, 1972-1977; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Mount Vernon Seminary and Junior College long range planning, 1965; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Mr. Pelham's folder--long range planning, 1964-1965; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - MVC Board of Directors--meetings of May 28 meeting, 1977; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - MVC report of examination, 1973; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - NEH grand proposal for arts and humanities expansion, 1972; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - New dormitory, 1970; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Presidential search committee, 1976-1977; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Special events committee, 1972-1973; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Women's committee, 1977; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Special events files, 1966-1977; Series 3
  The materials of this series are files concerning speical events held on campus at Mount Vernon, including concerts and assemblies. News concerning Peter Pelham and speeches he gave are also included in this series. The materials date from 1966-1977.
  - Antique show/Juilliard concert, 1976; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Chrissie McCutchen Award Character Excellence Cup, 1977; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - French Cup--commencement awards, 1966; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Harry S. Truman Scholarship, 1976; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Honors luncheon and assembly, 1972; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Pearl Bailey Benefit 1, 1977; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Pearl Bailey Benefit 2, 1977; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Pearl Bailey Benefit 3, 1977; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Pelham resignation press, 1977; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Peter Pelham newspaper articles and clippings, 1969-1977; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Stephens College speech, 1973; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Tradition and Change: The Crucial Years--speech, undated; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - A tribute to Peter Pelham, 1977; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Administrative files 1975-1977, Series 4
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  It appears that the box containing these files was transferred separately and Special Collections chose to retain the original order and make this material a separate series.
  This series contains administrative files dating from 1975-1977. They are concerning a wide range of topics including but not limited to admissions, alumnae affairs, annual fund, finance, public relations, and student affairs.
  - Admissions, 1975-1976; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Admissions ofice, 1976-1977; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Alumnae affairs, 1975-1976; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Alumnae office, 1976-1977; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Alumnae executive committee meetings, 1976-1977; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Annual fund, 1975-1976; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Annual fund, 1976-1977; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Annual fund meetings, 1976-1977; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Bookstore, 1976-1977; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Business office, 1975-1976; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Business office, 1976-1977; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Calendars: monthly, weekly, 1976-1977; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Career counseling, 1976-1977; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Continuing education, 1975-1977; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Continuing education #1, 1975-1976; Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Continuing education #2, 1975-1976; Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Cultural forums, 1976-1977; Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Finance and development, 1975-1976; Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Finance and development, 1976-1977; Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Financial aid, 1975-1977; Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Housing, 1976-1977; Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Library resource center, 1975-1976; Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Library consultants, 1968-1969; Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Library research council, 1976-1977; Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Neighborhood planning council, 1975-1976; Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Operations--use of facilities, 1976-1977; Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - President's office, 1975-1977; Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Public relations, 1975-1976; Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Publications, 1975-1977; Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Publications/public relations, 1974-1975; Series 4 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Registrar's office, 1975-1977; Series 4 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Student affairs, 1975-1976; Series 4 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Student affairs, 1976-1977; Series 4 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Student council, 1976-1977; Series 4 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Washington Area Feminist Theater, 1975-1976; Series 4 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Washington Institute for Women in Politics, 1976-1977; Series 4 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Washington Institute for Women in Politics #2, 1976-1977; Series 4 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Withdrawals, 1976-1977; Series 4 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Administrative files, 1969-1982; Series 5
  The materials in this series include administrative files from the office of Peter Pelham, including press clippings, financial materials, and meeting minutes from various committees. The materials range in date from 1969-1982.
  - Academic models and cost effectiveness: "retreat", 1974; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Ad hoc committee on student life, 1969-1970; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Administrative council, 1973-1974; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Administrative council, 1975-1976; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Advertising, 1975-1977; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Advertising, 1978-1979; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Baccalaureate/commencement speeches Peter Pelham, 1973-1977; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Board committee on foundation support, 1970-1979; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Center for Washington Learning Opportunities, 1973; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Christian Science Monitor, 1971; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Curriculum planning joint committee, 1972-1973; Series 5 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Debt/servicing/deficit liquidation, 1978-1979; Series 5 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Faculty; faculty staff retreat, 1974; Series 5 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Fiscal/academic planning Dr. Kells, 1974; Series 5 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Fundraising letters fiscal year, 1978; Series 5 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Intellectual Digest press coverage, 1972; Series 5 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - June committee re: academic programs, 1974; Series 5 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Media portfolio, 1972-1974; Series 5 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Modular calendar, 1971-1972; Series 5 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - MVC in print- miscellaneous clips, 1971-1976; Series 5 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous press clips, 1976-1979; Series 5 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Panorama, 1971; Series 5 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Potential faculty, 1976-1977; Series 5 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - President's remarks, undated; Series 5 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - President's advisory committee, 1975-1976; Series 5 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Press clips, 1975; Series 5 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Press clips, 1975-1976; Series 5 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Press clips, 1975-1976; Series 5 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Press coverage, 1976-1977; Series 5 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Press dinner- background material, 1982; Series 5 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Public relations, 1972-1982; Series 5 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Stagebill (ads), 1975; Series 5 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Stansbury, 1974-1975; Series 5 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Study abroad, 1972-1975; Series 5 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Unrestricted gifts, 1974-1980; Series 5 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Vice President and Dean's bi-weekly meetings, 1975; Series 5 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Washington Star and Washington Magazine ads, 1975; Series 5 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Women's colleges- background, 1973-1975; Series 5 (Box 11, Folder 12)